Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Denis Lanigan papers, 1955-1986 RL.00699
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Denis Lanigan papers
1955-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.00699
29.0 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Denis Lanigan was an executive who managed JWT Offices in Frankfurt, London and New York before being named Vice Chairman and Chief Operating Officer. Collection includes correspondence and memoranda, policy manuals and reports, account files and research reports that document Lanigan's career in JWT offices in Frankfurt and New York. Companies represented include Chevron, Kellogg, Kodak, Kraft, Nestle, Pepsi, R.J. Reynolds and Unilever. Acquired as part of the John. W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Denis Lanigan Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) Archives in 1987 and from the JWT Frankfurt Office in 1995.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1926 January 25 Denis George Lanigan born in London, England
1939-1944 Attended Drayton Manor School
1945-1948 Served in the Royal Air Force
1950 Received Master of Arts Degree in Economics from Kings College, Cambridge
1950-1952 Worked in Bank of England Overseas and Foreign Department
1952-1956 Joined Marketing Department of JWT Worked as an Account Representative for Unilever
1957 January Transferred to JWT-Frankfurt as Management Supervisor
1959 March Moved to New York Office as Account Supervisor for Unilever
1959 October 5 Married Jean Sanderson
1960-1964 Worked at JWT-Frankfurt as Joint Manager
1964-1966 Appointed Director of JWT-London, responsible for coordinating Unilever accounts worldwide
1966 February Succeeded Tom Sutton as Managing Director of JWT-London
1969 Elected Senior Vice-President of JWT parent corporation
1974 Named Executive Vice-President of JWT-Europe and elected to Board of Directors
1975 March Became Chairman of JWT-London Group Subsidiaries
1976 October Promoted to Chairman of JWT United Kingdom Group and President of European Division
1980 August Became a Vice Chairman in New York Office, responsible for finance and personnel worldwide
1982 January Named Vice Chairman-Chief Operating Officer, JWT-New York
1982 Elected to the Board of Directors of JWT Group, Inc.
1986 Dec. Retired from JWT
Denis and Jean Lanigan had two children, Mark born in 1960 and Katherine in 1962. Mr. Lanigan currently resides in London.
Collection Overview
Includes correspondence and memoranda, policy manuals and reports, account files and research reports that document Lanigan's career in JWT offices in Frankfurt and New York. Companies represented include Chevron, Kellogg, Kodak, Kraft, Nestle, Pepsi, R.J. Reynolds and Unilever. Acquired as part of the John. W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Processing Note
Organized into two series: Frankfurt Office; and New York Office.
Advertising -- Germany; Television advertising; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- Germany; Advertising -- Management; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Management; Pepsi-Cola Company; Kraft Foods Company; Lanigan, Denis, 1926-; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Eastman Kodak Company; Lever Brothers; Unilever (Firm)
- Frankfurt Office, 1958-1964
  Scope and Contents
  The Frankfurt Office series spans the years 1958 to 1964, with the bulk of the material dating from 1959 to 1960 and from 1963 to 1964. The papers primarily document activities of JWT's Frankfurt Office during the years Lanigan served as Joint Manager. Specific topics covered are efforts to increase and improve the use of television and print advertising in Europe, especially England and Germany; to improve coordination of international JWT Offices to better serve client interests; to increase European business; and to handle a variety of personnel, public relations, and marketing concerns. The papers consist of typed and handwritten correspondence, telexes and telegrams, memoranda, notes, reports, one photograph, press releases, speeches, contracts, newsletters, clippings, product samples, collateral literature and advertisements. Clients of the company represented in the collection include Chesebrough-Pond's, Findus, Ford, Johnson Wax (or Johnson-Gruenol), Kaufhof, Kraft, Lever-Sunlicht, Pan American Airways, Pepsi, Rowntree, Singer, Triumph, Warner-Lambert, Wick, and others. Correspondents include clients; executives from JWT offices such as George Black, David Campbell-Harris, Bill Hinks, Constance B. Ivie, Don Johnston, Jens von Leutzendorff, Sam Meek, D. M. Saunders, Lubertus Smilde, Norman Strouse, Thomas Sutton, and Edward G. Wilson; media consultants such as Eric Boden; and persons affiliated with various companies and organizations.
  Approximately 70 percent of the collection is in English and the remainder is in German, with the exception of very small amounts of French, Italian, and Dutch. English is the sole language of the Articles subseries and the Layton Awards subseries, and the predominant language in the Correspondence subseries, the Other JWT Offices subseries, and the Meetings subseries. English and German are used in roughly equal amounts in the Clients subseries, the New Business subseries and the Marketing and Research/Abteilung Marktforschung subseries. German is the predominant language in the Memoranda/Haus-Mitteilungen subseries.
  The Correspondence subseries documents Lanigan's transition from JWT's New York Office to the Frankfurt office, coordination between the Frankfurt and London Offices, Frankfurt's day-to-day operations, German and American attitudes toward advertising, and reviews of a German-made film on U.S. advertising called Bilder aus der neuen Welt (Pictures from the New World). The film profiles JWT, Benson and Mather, Dr. Dichter, Ogilvy, and McCann-Erickson advertising agencies. The subseries also contains information on accounts, including market strategies, difficulties in dealing with the European management of Playtex, the coordination of Unilever, acquisition of the Pan Am account in Vienna, and the production of television ads for various clients. Correspondents from the New York office include Paul Albright, George Black, Aldis Butler, M. Lee Calvert, Robert Carman, Malcolm Davis, Peter Dunham, Robert Hawes, William Hinks, Connie Ivie, Sam Meek, O'Neill Ryan, Norman Strouse, Clifford Snyder, and Lubertus Smilde, and from the London office Thomas G. Hardie and D.M. Saunders. Other correspondents in this subseries include persons affiliated with various media consulting firms; economic research organizations; the advertising agencies Troost and McCann-Erickson; and Booz, Allen, and Hamilton International; and organizations such as Advertiser's Weekly, the American Chamber of Commerce in Germany, and the Gesellschaft Werbeagenturen.
  The Other J. Walter Thompson Offices subseries consists of correspondence between Denis Lanigan and executives from JWT's international offices. Files for the London and New York Offices contain the most material, while Amsterdam, Milan, and Paris are also substantial among the thirty-five offices documented. Topics include aspects of film production for clients, the impact of legislation and public perception on advertising internationally, training and personnel matters, Frankfurt Office visitors, and international public relations for JWT. Some issues that are covered specifically include 1962 total advertising expenditures in the UK; Lord Robens' speech on advertising and politics; a major German exhibit on advertising and the consumer (“Der umworbene Mensch”); information on outdoor advertising in Italy; market research on the German beer and bread markets; the need for establishing a JWT Office in Vienna; the development, testing and introduction of new Lever products in Germany such as CD and SIGNAL; efforts to improve the overall quality of film advertising in Germany including the unsuccessful attempt to recruit well-known theater director Peter Zadek; and an evaluation of the need for better assessing client conflicts of interest, arising in part from the conflict between Canada Mink and the Swedish SAGA Mink as JWT clients in Europe. Correspondents from the London Office include James Archibald, Jeremy Bullmore, Christopher Cross, Bill Hinks, Norman Basset, Carl Ivens, Elizabeth Oxley, Michael Patmore, Douglas Saunders, and Tom Sutton; and from the New York Office, Gordon Conley and Edward Wilson among others. Current and prospective accounts discussed in this subseries include Alcan, Brinkmann, Bristol Myers, Burroughs, Braemar, Brillo, Canada Mink, Champion, Chesebrough-Ponds, Dunlop, Eastman Kodak, Findus, Ford, Kaufhof, Kelloggs, Kraft, Lintex, Lux, Merrill Lynch, Nestle, Oxo, Singer, Scott, Therachemie, Triumph, and Vic's (UK name of Vick's/Wick).
  The Clients subseries consists of materials pertaining to JWT's day-to-day work for its clients, including market strategies, campaign development, and the production of advertisements. It includes background information on JWT's relationship with Ford in Germany and Switzerland, a review of Kraft advertising in Germany, and information on special promotions for Pepsi in Europe. Well-documented accounts in this subseries include: Chesebrough Pond's, Dunlop, Ford, Intercontinental Hotels, Johnson Wax, Litton Industries, Kaufhof, Kraft, Maggi, Merrill Lynch, Norda, Playtex, Pepsi, SAGA, SIGNAL (a Lever product), Triumph, Warner-Lambert, and Wrigley.
  The New Business subseries documents Frankfurt's strategies to acquire new clients. The subseries includes both successful and unsuccessful new business presentations for the following companies and organizations: Beecham/Ribena, Constructa, Dow Chemical, Eastman Kodak, Famous Artist Schools, FAZ, Horlicks, Jopa, Langeberg Sales, Oetker, Osram, Philips, Lever, SEL, Singer, and the World Coffee Promotion Committee.
  The Memoranda/Hausmitteilungen subseries offers insight into the internal policy and communications of the Frankfurt Office. The subseries specifically documents shifts in the Marketing Department's organization and training, information on television advertising, art-buying, the company's media archive, personnel policies, and daily operations. Clients discussed in this subseries include Findus, Florida Citrus Growers, Nordsee, RCA, SIGNAL, and Scott.
  The Meetings subseries documents Lanigan's participation in JWT European Managers' Meetings. Topics discussed at the meetings include JWT's international public relations, management coordination of international accounts, ideas for new business presentations, the economic implications of the European common market, and interoffice communication and exchange of personnel.
  The Articles subseries contains advertising and promotional plans for JWT agricultural clients (California Raisin Advisory Board, Pineapple Growers Association, Olive Advisory Board). Other topics include copy research and grocery trade; advertising effects on economic growth; and international advertising markets and campaigns.
  The Marketing and Research/Abteilung Marktforschung subseries documents research projects, correspondence (primarily with the New York Office), and memoranda of Frankfurt's Marketing and Research division (Abteilung Marktforschung).
  The Layton Awards Series consists of materials relating to the annual Layton Awards for British advertising, an event sponsored by the graphics firm C and E Layton.
  Related Materials
  For related material, see other collections in the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, especially the papers of other Frankfurt office executives, the Frankfurt advertisements collection, and the Frankfurt video collection.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1964 (bulk 1959-1960)
    Scope and Contents note
    Consists of letters to and from Lanigan as well as copies of correspondence from or to other executives of the Frankfurt Office, including Peter Gilow. Also contains interoffice communications such as notes, memoranda, and reports, as well as some personal correspondence.
    Arrangement note
    Although Lever-Sunlicht is a 100% subsidiary of Unilever, JWT-Frankfurt's correspondence with this client is filed under the letter L and not U. Similarly Eastman Kodak Company is referred to in correspondence as Kodak, and files under K, and special to the German filing system are the entries of Sch and St following S. Arranged chronologically by year, then alphabetically by correspondent.
    - 1959, March-Sept.Whitbread (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960,A-Z, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960,A-Z, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964,A-Z, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Other J. Walter Thompson Offices, 1958-1964 (bulk 1959-1960, 1963-1964)
    Constitutes Denis Lanigan's incoming and outgoing correspondence with over thirty-five JWT offices worldwide. It contains letters, telexes and telegrams, memoranda, notes, clippings, client lists, printed materials, policy statements, reports, drafts of speeches, and meeting minutes.
    Arranged alphabetically by city, then chronologically.
    - Amsterdam, 1959-1960, 1963-64 (Box 1)
      - J. Walter Thompson Amsterdam Newsletter, JWT News - Amsterdam, 1960-1964 (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 1)
    - Antwerp, 1959-1960, 1963-1964
      - J. Walter Thompson Antwerp Newsletter, JWT Company Belgian Bulletin, 1960-1961 (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 1)
    - Bombay, 1960, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Buenos Aires, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Calcutta, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Cape Town, 1959, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Caracas, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Chicago, 1959-1960, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Columbo, 1960, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Detroit, 1960, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Durban, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Johannesburg, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Karachi, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Lima, 1960, 1964 (Box 1)
    - London:
      - 1958 Dec.-1959 Sept. (Box 1)
      - 1959-1960,A-Z, 7 folders (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964,A-Z, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Los Angeles, 1959-1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Madras, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Manila, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Mexico City, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Milan:
      - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
      - J. Walter Thompson Milan Newsletters, Notizario J.W.T. - Italia and Qui...Thompson -Italia (transferred to the JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 2)
    - Montevideo, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Montreal, 1960 (Box 2)
    - New Delhi, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - New York:
      - 1959 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1964,A-Z, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - J. Walter Thompson New York Newsletter, JWT Company News, 1959-1962 (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 2)
    - Paris, 1958-1960, 1963-1964
      - J. Walter Thompson Paris Newsletter, Informations JWT Paris, 1961and 1963 (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 2)
    - Rio de Janeiro, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Salisbury, 1960 (Box 2)
    - San Francisco, 1959-1960, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - San Juan, 1960-1961, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Santiago de Chile, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Sydney, 1960, 1963
      - J. Walter Thompson Sydney Newsletter, JWT Company Australian News (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 2)
    - Tokyo, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Toronto, 1959-1960, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Vancouver, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Vienna:
      - Correspondence, 1963,A-Z (Box 2)
      - Memoranda/Haus-Mitteilungen, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Zurich, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Clients, 1959-1964 (bulk 1959-1960, 1963-1964)
    Comprised of call reports (Kontaktberichte), market research, minutes (Protokolle), clippings, invitations, contracts, letters of terms, purchase orders, articles, speeches, bills, ads, graphs, and correspondence with and regarding JWT clients.
    Although Lever-Sunlicht is a 100% subsidiary of Unilever, JWT-Frankfurt's correspondence with this client is filed under the letter L and not U. Similarly Eastman Kodak Company is referred to in correspondence as Kodak, and files under K. Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by client.
    - 1959-1960,A-T, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964,A-W, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964,A-Fi (Box 2)
    - 1963, Ford, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964,H-K (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964,M-Pe (Box 3)
    - 1963-1964,Po-T (Box 3)
  - New Business, 1963-1964
    Comprised of correspondence, notes, sample contracts, charts, memos, public relations action proposals, articles, advertisements, speeches, proxies, consumer surveys, and research policy statements relating to the acquisition of new business accounts for JWT.
    Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by company or organization.
    - 1963-1964,A-Z, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Memoranda/Haus-Mitteilungen, 1959-1962
    Consists of internal correspondence, statements of company policy, drafts of speeches, newsletters, other publications of JWT's Presse- und Informationsdienste (media and information services), and lists of print media in the company archive. Also includes the charter of the “JWT Dinner-Club,” an organization for JWT's male executives.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1959-1960, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - JWT Report Frankfurt, 1959 Apr.-1962 Feb.,and Common Market Newsletter, 1960 (Box 3)
      - J. Walter Thompson London Newsletter, Round the Square, 1960, Oct.(transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 3)
  - Meetings, 1962-1964
    Comprised of agendas, minutes, memos, correspondence, and one photograph relating to European Managers' Meetings. Includes a list of dates and locations of all European Managers' Meetings that took place from 1958to 1964.
    - European Managers Meeting: (Box 3)
      - 1962, Feb.,London (Box 3)
      - 1962, June,Frankfurt (Box 3)
      - 1962, Oct.,Milan (Box 3)
      - 1963, Jan.,Amsterdam (Box 3)
      - J. Walter Thompson Amsterdam Newsletter, JWT News - Amsterdam, 1963 (transferred to JWT Newsletter Collection) (Box 3)
      - 1963, June, Frankfurt, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1963, Oct., Brussels (Box 3)
      - 1964, Feb., London (Box 3)
  - Articles, 1958-1961
    Includes JWT Research Department's bulletins, JWT news releases, speeches, writings, copies of JWT house advertisements, a report on copy research, clippings, articles, newsletters, and an international advertising convention's program.
    - 1958-1962, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Marketing and Research/Abteilung Marktforschung, 1959-1960
    Comprised of European Research Meeting minutes, research projects, speeches, reports, minutes (Protokolle), correspondence, and memoranda. Includes a 1960speech by Norman H. Strouse which introduced a series of marketing seminars; monthly reports on work for clients and products such as Dunlop, Elida, Ford, Kraft, Lux, Nordsee, Pepsi, Ponds, and Wick; and a memo on the 1960 Esomar Conference.
    - 1959-1960,Correspondence (Box 3)
    - 1959-1960,Memoranda (Box 3)
  - Layton Awards, 1960-1962
    Contains notes, invitations, letters, exhibit catalogs, rules and entry forms, speeches, articles and correspondence relating to the Layton Awards. Includes a 1960 speech by Prince Philip criticizing the current state of British advertising.
    - 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 3)
- New York Office, 1970-1986; 1
  - J. Walter Thompson, 1955-1986; 1
    - 1982 in Review, 1983 (Box 4)
    - 1983 Plan, 1982-1983; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1984 Company Plan, 1983 (Box 4)
    - 1984 Plan, 1983 (Box 4)
    - 420 Lexington (Greybar Bldg.), 1981-1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 420 Lexington (Greybar Bldg.)--Tenants, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
    - 466 Lexington--21st and 3rd floor projects, 1981 (Box 4)
    - 466 Lexington--Budget, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Events press, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Executive dining room, 1983 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Floor plans, 1980-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--General, 1979-1983; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Move meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Office move press, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Olympia & York, 1983 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Phone plans, 1980-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Postal address, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Real estate and acquisition selection criteria, 1980-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Rent allocation, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Rent and leases, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Status reports, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - 466 Lexington--Work area requests, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Account planning, 1975-1983 (Box 6)
    - Agencies going public, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Agency brand names, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Agency compensation, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - Agency compensation study, 1980 (Box 48)
    - Agency performance evaluations, 1981 (Box 6)
    - AMI database, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Appointment of Lanigan as Vice Chairman, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Asia-Pacific, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Australia, 1981-1985; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Australia--Acquisitions, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Australia--Acquisitions--Begg, Dow, Priday, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Australia--Acquisitions--Kestell McManus, Lloyd Graham, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Australia--Restructure, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Awards concept, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
    - Board meetings, 1982-1985; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Brouillard Communications, 1982-1985; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Cable Capsules, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - CableShop, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
    - Canada, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Canada, 1981-1985; 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Canada--Acquisition--Watson Advertising, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Canada--Board meeting, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Canada--Montreal Board meeting, 1982 (Box 8)
    - Canada--Operational Review, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Canada--Toronto, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Canada--Watson Advertising lease, 1980 (Box 48)
    - Caracas, 1982-1985 (Box 9)
    - Chicago office space--John Buck report, 1981 (Box 9)
    - Chile, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Company priorities, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Computers, 1982-1984 (Box 9)
    - Copies of mailings, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Corporate culture, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Credit policy, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Data processing, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - David Campbell Harris trip to Turkey, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Dividend policy, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Don Johnston, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    - EPCOT (World Advertising Forum), 1983-1984; 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Ethics Committee, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Europe Operational Review, 1983 (Box 10)
    - Europe professional development, 1983 (Box 10)
    - Europe region, 1984 (Box 10)
    - European Managers Meeting, 1981-1986; 5 folders (Box 11)
    - European Regional Operating Committee (EROC), 1983-1986; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - EROC position paper on sponsorships (Box 11)
    - Executive Committee, 1981-1985; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - France, 1980-1983; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Germany, 1980-1982; 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Germany, 1983-1985; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Germany--Dusseldorf Office opening, 1983 (Box 13)
    - Germany--Frankfurt press, including 30th anniversary (German), 1982 (Box 48)
    - Germany--Hamburg Office opening (English and German), 1983 (Box 48)
    - Germany--Markenplan, 1981 (Box 13)
    - Germany--Vitasound, 1981 (Box 13)